<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>linux on Goofing Osamu</title>
    <link>/tags/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in linux on Goofing Osamu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Debian Workstation (usability) (v2023)</title>
      <link>/en/2023/02/25/debian-usability-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2023/02/25/debian-usability-2023/</guid>
      <description>This is an updated guide. The older deprecated guide was used as its base.
Workstation usability Let me update note on configuring and administrating my workstation under post-Debian Bookworm (12) GNU/Linux in testing.
This is non-hardware specific notes and tips.
For the hardware specific notes and tips, see:
Thinkpad T14 Sony Vaio SVT1313 System installation Initial installation by debian-installer The initial installation by the debian-installer should skip &amp;ldquo;Desktop environment&amp;rdquo; task to make it light GUI-less install.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development system (4)</title>
      <link>/en/2022/08/20/dev-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2022/08/20/dev-04/</guid>
      <description>Package repo on github page Since Githubs offer nice web site hosting service, I decided to host my private build results there at http://osamuaoki.github.io/debian.
This let me skip running the web server as described in Local private package repo.
Since Debian Salsa runs Gitlab and Gitlab also offers equivalent web site hosting service, one should be able to do the same there. But considering tight resource constaints there, it may not be a good idea to do this on Salsa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Usability tips: Backup and snapshots</title>
      <link>/en/2021/11/02/backup-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2021/11/02/backup-1/</guid>
      <description>Backup and snapshot For backup, data needs to be moved to physically separate device. rsync ... is my choice to do this.
For snapshot, data can stay on the same device . btrfs subvolume snapshot ... is my choice to do this.
I created bss script to help me do these easily and its examples contain key parts of the settings. Here are the basic tricks used in them..
Secure backup In order to securely backup private data using non-secure remote storage, data needs to be encrypted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development system (2)</title>
      <link>/en/2021/04/09/dev-02/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2021/04/09/dev-02/</guid>
      <description>Local private package repo After reading https://wiki.debian.org/DebianRepository/Setup checking their popularity, I decided to go with reprepro package.
Here, I follow https://wiki.debian.org/DebianRepository/SetupWithReprepro (It was slightly outdated. I update it.)
Setting up an web server $ sudo apt install apache2 Now you can see a nice &amp;ldquo;Default Page&amp;rdquo; at &amp;ldquo;[::1]&amp;rdquo; (or &amp;ldquo;127.0.0.1&amp;rdquo; for IPV4) using browser.
Let&amp;rsquo;s create a simple directory tree for single distribution case.
$ sudo bash -i # mkdir -p /var/www/html/debian # cat &amp;gt; /etc/apache2/conf-available/repos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development system (1)</title>
      <link>/en/2021/04/03/dev-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2021/04/03/dev-01/</guid>
      <description>Development infrastructure In order to keep development setups to be simple and robust, I changed development infrastructure.
For package test build, I decided to move to schroot. For package build, I decided to move to sbuild (a schroot wrapper). For package test for each GUI setups, I decided to set up KVM. (I was suffering sudden cowbuilder failures. That was another motivation.)
Planned infrastructure includes:
APT proxy on the host WS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debian Workstation (usability) (old)</title>
      <link>/en/2021/01/15/debian-usability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2021/01/15/debian-usability/</guid>
      <description>This is an outdated deprecated guide. Please read the updated guide.
Workstation usability Let me keep up note on configuring and administrating my workstation under post-Debian Bullseye (11) GNU/Linux in testing.
This is non-hardware specific notes and tips.
Installer installed extra packages After the initial installation, packages with Priority: values required, important and standard are installed. In addition to these packages, I see the installer installs following extra packages:
busybox console-setup discover grub-efi-amd64 initramfs-tools installation-report keyboard-configuration laptop-detect libcap2-bin linux-image-amd64 lsb-base popularity-contest shim-signed task-desktop task-english task-laptop tasksel usbutils Initial setup Running initial-setup script found at my repository should set up basics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ThinkPad T14 Gen 1 (AMD)</title>
      <link>/en/2021/01/07/thinkpad-t14-gen-1-amd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2021/01/07/thinkpad-t14-gen-1-amd/</guid>
      <description>Let me keep up note on configuring and administrating my ThinkPad T14 Gen 1 (AMD) under Debian GNU/Linux. This is hardware specific tips.
My system has 2 NVMe SSDs:
AMD Ryzen™ 5 PRO 4650U &amp;ndash; 6 cores, 12 threads 32GB (PC4-25600 DDR4 SDRAM) &amp;ndash; after adding aftermarket Transcend 16GB SDRAM (JM3200HSE-16G [SODIMM DDR4 PC4-25600 16GB]) WDC PC SN520 SDAPMUW-128G-1001 (20370001) &amp;ndash; Original Western Digital 128GB SSD TS2TMTE220S (42B8T4EA) &amp;ndash; Aftermarket Transcend 2TB SSD Official Information Sources T14 Gen 1 (type 20UD, 20UE) Laptop (ThinkPad) Product Home Removal and Replacement Videos - ThinkPad T14 Gen 1 Forum Adding 2TB SSD (2280 both side) The original Western Digital 128GB PCIe SSD (2242, IC on top side only) is removed and moved with thermal pad to the unused PCIe slot intended for WAN card.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dmesg for SATA</title>
      <link>/en/2020/04/29/dmesg-sata/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2020/04/29/dmesg-sata/</guid>
      <description>dmesg from SATA After having a loose SATA cable problem and fixed it, I happen to see dmesg as:
$ sudo dmesg ... [ 2.373152] sd 0:0:0:0: [sda] 937703088 512-byte logical blocks: (480 GB/447 GiB) [ 2.373156] sd 0:0:0:0: [sda] Write Protect is off [ 2.373158] sd 0:0:0:0: [sda] Mode Sense: 00 3a 00 00 [ 2.373165] sd 0:0:0:0: [sda] Write cache: enabled, read cache: enabled, doesn&amp;#39;t support DPO or FUA [ 2.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
