<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>vim on Goofing Osamu</title>
    <link>/tags/vim/</link>
    <description>Recent content in vim on Goofing Osamu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 05:22:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/vim/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Re-learning Vim (3)</title>
      <link>/en/2021/09/12/vim-learn-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 05:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2021/09/12/vim-learn-3/</guid>
      <description>Neovim migration After finding out Neovim (nvim) starts up 30%-40% faster than Vim 8 probably due to asynchronous processing and more effective use of multi-core modern CPU, I decided to migrate to nvim. Then lua thing got my attention. Since nvim source package for version 0.5 was available in Debian experimental, I made a local package from it. So I am in good shape to try the latest lua scripts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Re-learning Vim (2)</title>
      <link>/en/2019/09/24/vim-learn-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2019/09/24/vim-learn-2/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s review how I initialize Vim and use a few interesting packages.
Please note that I now manage package directly via the Vim 8&amp;rsquo;s native package management framework with packadd! without using so-called package managers.
Vim general settings (packages) As of 2021-09-02, I mostly use the latest version from github for some fancy fast developing packages but also use older mature packages from Debian vim-scripts package.
vim-sensible &amp;ndash; basics
matchit &amp;ndash; provided by vim securemodelines &amp;ndash; vim-scripts</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Re-learning Vim (1)</title>
      <link>/en/2019/09/17/vim-learn-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2019/09/17/vim-learn-1/</guid>
      <description>I could use Vim as a basic editor with TKL-keyboard while tapping some keys multiple times. This was functional but not so elegant!
I decided to re-learn Vim to use it properly. Here is my learning memo.
For simplicity, I may use ^F to mean CTRL-F.
Concept Use default vim (minimum configuration, if possible). Use as much native functionalities. Don&amp;rsquo;t force Vim to behave like another program. 50%/60%-keyboard ready. Use no cursor keys, if possible.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
