<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>javascript on Goofing Osamu</title>
    <link>/tags/javascript/</link>
    <description>Recent content in javascript on Goofing Osamu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/javascript/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>GNOME extensions</title>
      <link>/en/2023/06/17/gnome-extensions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2023/06/17/gnome-extensions/</guid>
      <description>After learning to use GNOME shell extension: unsafe-mode-menu for workaround in GNOME shell, I checked other available and interesting GNOME extensions. Resources checked are:
*D: *.deb package available *U: 15 Best GNOME Extensions for Ubuntu (2022 Edition) *L: 30 Best GNOME Extensions for Ubuntu in 2023 *N: Top +30 Best GNOME Extensions | 2023 Updated *M: 10 Must Have GNOME Shell Extensions for Customizing Your Linux Desktop in 2022 *A: Awesome GNOME I used local install approach of GNOME extension to ~/.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GNOME shell</title>
      <link>/en/2023/06/16/gnome-shell/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2023/06/16/gnome-shell/</guid>
      <description>This is how I resolved GNOME shell configuration trouble and came up as Debian Workstation (usability) (v2023) &amp;ndash; Keyboard shortcut customization (GNOME Settings – custom shortcut)
Keyboad shortcuts stopped working Since 2022, tricks written in my old キーボード入力モード選択 and its English translated description Debian Workstation (usability) (old)) &amp;ndash; Keyboard shortcut customization (GNOME Settings) stopped working for me.
This breakage seemed to have happened with changes made in 2022.
My initial reaction to brokage of trick method was this may be caused by changes of javascript codes in gnome-shell.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
