<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ansible on Goofing Osamu</title>
    <link>/tags/ansible/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ansible on Goofing Osamu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/ansible/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ansible (3)</title>
      <link>/en/2024/02/20/ansible-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2024/02/20/ansible-3/</guid>
      <description>Here is a series of memos of me trying to use ansible on Debian 12 (bookworm).
FYI: Test code github repo
Recap of my trials of playbooks Up to here, I tried simple playbooks in which a playbook runs in order from top to bottom.
Let me read over again &amp;ldquo;Playbook execution&amp;rdquo;:
Playbook execution A playbook runs in order from top to bottom. Within each play, tasks also run in order from top to bottom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ansible (2)</title>
      <link>/en/2024/02/19/ansible-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2024/02/19/ansible-2/</guid>
      <description>Here is a series of memos of me trying to use ansible on Debian 12 (bookworm).
FYI: Test code github repo
Searching roles in Ansible Galaxy and ansible-galaxy Ansible Galaxy is a curation site for Ansible scripts. They are offered in 2 formats:
Roles &amp;ndash; data downloaded as &amp;ldquo;git clone ...&amp;rdquo;. Collections &amp;ndash; data downloaded in &amp;ldquo;*.tar.gz&amp;rdquo; format. Once some interesting script is found from the search on the Ansible Galaxy web site, execute the listed command.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ansible (1)</title>
      <link>/en/2024/02/17/ansible-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/2024/02/17/ansible-1/</guid>
      <description>I realize that it is about time to getting organized for my system setup in a way better than making notes and writing shell scripts.
I decided to deploy Ansible for localhost only with CLI to help me get organized and learn Ansible.
Since upstream Ansible documentation addresses more generic remote host usages and is too much to digest, this memo should be a good minimal use case for me to get started.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
